Guide to the Isaku and Emi Kida Papers TAM.165
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Isaku and Emi Kida Papers
1929-2002, undated
1980-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kida, Emi, 1908-2001
Kida, Isaku, 1905-1996
Onuma, Susan
TAM.165
6 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, and 1 oversized folder in a shared box
Isaku and Emi Kida were the publishers of the Hokubei Shimpo, later the New York Nichibei, a Japanese and English newspaper published in New York, New York from 1945 to 1993. The collection contains partial business records for the Hokubei Shimpo and the New York Nichibei with Emi Kida's personal papers making up the bulk of the collection. The collection dates are 1929-2002, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1983 and 1993. The majority of the collection is in English, although most personal and business correspondence is in Japanese.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Susan J. Onuma, executor of the estate of Emi Kida in 2004. The accession number associated with this gift is 2007.028.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in six series. Series I is arranged alphabetically by type of document and Series II is arranged chronologically. Series III is arranged alphabetically, with Japanese language materials preceding materials arranged according to whom they belonged, with an alphabetical arrangement according to type of document within that arrangement. Series IV is arranged alphabetically by type of document and then chronologically within that arrangement. Series V is arranged chronologically and Series VI is arranged alphabetically.
The series arrangement is as follows:
Series I. The Hokubei Shimpo and The New York Nichibei Publisher's Files, 1972, 1980-1998 Series II. Cards and Correspondence, 1957-2000 Series III. Biographical Materials, 1929, 1979-2002 Series IV. Financial records, 1945, 1959-2000 Series V. Photographs, 1934, 1956-1957, 1968-1978, 1985-2000, undated Series VI. Publications, 1964-2002
Biographical Note
Isaku Kida was born Nobuyuki Kawase in Fukuoka, Japan in 1905. He graduated from Aoyama Academy in 1928 with a degree in education and taught English in a junior high school for two years before immigrating to the United States in 1930 in order to study theology at Oberlin College. He left Oberlin and moved to New York, New York in 1932. He became interested in Communism and changed his name to Isaku Kida in order to protect his family in Japan from any negative association with him.
Kida joined the Hokubei Shimpo in December 1945. Despite having no previous newspaper experience, he moved up through the ranks, becoming the chief editor in 1949, chief executive in 1952, and finally president, director, general manager, and managing editor in 1977. Kida contributed to, edited, and published the paper until failing health forced him to retire and cease publication in 1993. He died in 1996.
Emi Kida was born on October 13, 1919 in Ogaki City in the Gifu Prefecture of Japan. She studied the traditional women's arts of embroidery, ikebana (flower arranging), and cooking at the Doshisha Women's College. In 1955, she was introduced to Isaku Kida by their mutual friend, Asae Konokawa. They married in Tokyo in the spring of 1958, and Emi immigrated to the United States later that year.
In New York, Emi managed the newspaper's finances and distribution, and set the type for each issue by hand. The Kidas purchased a Japanese word processor in 1980, which freed up a substantial amount of Emi's time and allowed her to report on cultural events for the newspaper. The Kidas lived on a strict budget and relied heavily on donations and advertisements to keep the newspaper in circulation. Emi worked at the newspaper until it ceased publication in 1993. She remained very involved in Japanese American community activities, in particular with the Japanese American Association of New York, the Japanese American United Church, and the Japanese American Social Services. She died in 2002.
Scope and Contents
The Isaku and Emi Kida Papers span from 1929 through 2002 and contain some business records of the Hokubei Shimpo and the New York Nichibei and Emi Kida's personal papers. The business records of the newspapers and their publisher, the Japanese American News Corporation, include financial documents and correspondence with other news organizations, including the Japan/New York Publishing Corporation, the Kyodo News Service, the OCS News, and the North American Post Publishing, Inc. The bulk of the correspondence is in Japanese.
Emi Kida's personal papers consititute the bulk of the collection and include correspondence, Christmas cards, ledgers, appointment books, photographs, exhibition catalogues, stage bills, and directories and newsletters from Japanese American churches and her alma mater, Doshisha Women's College. The bulk of Emi's correspondence, all of her ledgers and appointment books, and some of the printed material are in Japanese.
Separated Materials
In May 2016, issues of the Hokubei Shimpo and the New York Nichibei, dating from 1946 to 1993, were transferred to the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Japanese American Newspapers (TAM 688).
Japanese |z New York (State) |z New York.; Correspondence.; Japanese business enterprises |z United States.; New York Nichibei.; Photographs.; Newspapers.; Japanese Americans -- Social conditions.; Ledgers (account books); Hokubei Shimpo.; Japanese American newspapers.; Japanese |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs.; Appointment books.; Japanese American business enterprises |z New York (State) |z New York.; Japanese American News Corporation; Japanese American United Church; Onuma, Susan
- Series I. The Hokubei Shimpo and the New York Nichibei Publisher's Files, 1972, 1980-1998, undated; 0.1 Linear Feet in 4 folders
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains materials from 1972 through 2001 that document the business activities of the Japanese American News Corporation, the publisher of the Hokubei Shimpo and the New York Nichibei. The series contains correspondence with other news organizations, including the Japan/New York Publishing Corporation, the Kyodo News Service, OCS News, and North American Post Publishing, Inc. Business cards, the New York Nichibei Directory for 1972, and the Newsman's Hand-Book document contacts within the Japanese American publishing community. The entirety of material in this series is in Japanese.
  - Business cards, 1981-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business correspondence, 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New York Nichibei Directory, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newsman's Hand-Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II. Cards and Correspondence, 1957-2000, undated; 1 Linear Feet in 1 record carton
  This series contains letters and Christmas cards sent to Isaku and Emi Kida. The cards and letters are from the late 1950s through 2000, with the bulk of the material from the 1990s. The majority of the correspondence is in Japanese.
  - Cards and correspondence, 1957-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-19, Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Series III. Biographical Materials, 1929, 1979-2002, undated; 0.2 Linear Feet in 8 folders
  This series contains items from Isaku's memorial service in 1996; his time as a theology student at Oberlin College in the late 1920s; his curriculum vita from 1995; and an oral history conducted with him in the 1980s. Also in this series are Isaku and Emi Kida's wills and multiple awards granted to the Kidas by the Japanese American Association of New York, Inc. and the government of Japan.
  - Japanese Language Biographical Materials, 1985, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kida, Emi--Will, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kida, Isaku and Emi Kida--Awards, 1979, 1986, 1994-1998 (Box 2, Folder 7, Box 7, Folder 6, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003)
  - Kida, Isaku--Curriculum Vita, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Kida, Isaku--Oberlin College, 1929, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Kida, Isaku--Obituary and Funeral Materials, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kida, Isaku--Oral History, 1983, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Kida, Isaku--Will, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series IV. Financial records, 1945, 1959-2000, undated; 3 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons
  The series contains Japanese American News Corporation stock certificates and Isaku and Emi Kida's personal bank statements, tax returns, calendars, and ledgers. The ledgers document nearly 45 years of Emi's life. The majority of the entries are in Japanese.
  - Bank statements, 1998-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Calendars, 2000-2002 (Box 5, Folder 1-2, Folder 5)
  - Ledgers, 1959-2002 (Box 2, Folder 17-26, Box 5, Folder 3-4, Box 4, Folder 1-17, Box 3, Folder 1-16)
  - Stock Certificates for the Japanese American News Corporation, 1945, 1969, 1982, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Tax returns, 1960-1976, 1993-1994, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
- Series V. Photographs, 1934, 1956-1957, 1968-1978, 1985-2000, undated; 0.2 Linear Feet in 15 folders
  The material in this series dates from 1934 through 2000 with the bulk of the material from 2000. Included are portraits of Isaku and Emi Kida as well as snapshots of award ceremonies, New York City, and Emi's personal vacations to Disney World and Italy.
  - Photographs, 1934, 1956-1957, 1968-1978, 1985-2000, undated (Box 5, Folder 6-20)
- Series VI. Publications, 1964-2002; 1.5 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
  This series contains printed materials documenting Emi Kida's personal interests and activities as well as some of the cultural events she may have attended as a reporter for the New York Nichibei. The printed materials date between 1964 and 2002, with the majority from the 1990s. Included are newsletters and other publications of the Japanese American United Church and the Doshisha Women's College. Exhibition catalogues and Stagebills document some of the cultural events Emi may have covered for the New York Nichibei, including concerts at Carnegie Hall and Lincoln Center. Other organizations and institutions represented in this series include the Japan Society, the Japanese American Association of New York, the Japanese American Social Services, Inc., and Oberlin College. The Doshisha Women's College files contain two small volumes written by Emi's lifelong friend, Asae Konokawa. Konokawa's writings record the role of her husband, Seiichi Konokawa, in the establishment of the Hokubei Shimpo; her work as a reporter for the newspaper; and the beginning of the Kidas' relationship.
  - Carnegie Hall 100th Anniversary and Japanese theater programs, 1966-1967, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Doshisha Women's College, 1965-1973, 1984, 1992-2002 (Box 5, Folder 21-26)
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1974-1998 (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
  - Flowers and Gardening, 1964, 1977, 1993-1994, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Japan Society, 1994-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Japanese American Association of New York, 1990-2002, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Japanese American Social Services, Inc., 1993-1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Japanese American United Church, 1974, 1982, 1988-2002 (Box 6, Folder 4-6)
  - Look Culture Club Magazine, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Oberlin College, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Stagebills, 1993-1998 (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Stagebills, 1998-2002 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Union Japanese Church of Westchester, 1994-1998 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Zipangu, 1995-1997 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)